<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="shell_surface_intersection_observer_v1">
  <copyright>
    Copyright © 2025 outfoxxed

    Permission to use, copy, modify, distribute, and sell this
    software and its documentation for any purpose is hereby granted
    without fee, provided that the above copyright notice appear in
    all copies and that both that copyright notice and this permission
    notice appear in supporting documentation, and that the name of
    the copyright holders not be used in advertising or publicity
    pertaining to distribution of the software without specific,
    written prior permission.  The copyright holders make no
    representations about the suitability of this software for any
    purpose.  It is provided "as is" without express or implied
    warranty.

    THE COPYRIGHT HOLDERS DISCLAIM ALL WARRANTIES WITH REGARD TO THIS
    SOFTWARE, INCLUDING ALL IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND
    FITNESS, IN NO EVENT SHALL THE COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY
    SPECIAL, INDIRECT OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES OR ANY DAMAGES
    WHATSOEVER RESULTING FROM LOSS OF USE, DATA OR PROFITS, WHETHER IN
    AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, NEGLIGENCE OR OTHER TORTIOUS ACTION,
    ARISING OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE USE OR PERFORMANCE OF
    THIS SOFTWARE.
  </copyright>

  <description summary="protocol for observing intersection between surfaces and toplevels">
    This protocol allows clients to detect when a toplevel window intersects
    with a region relative to a client surface. This is intended to support
    desktop shell components that wish to avoid covering or being covered by
    a window, such as docks.

    The key words "must", "must not", "required", "shall", "shall not",
    "should", "should not", "recommended",  "may", and "optional" in this
    document are to be interpreted as described in IETF RFC 2119.

    Warning! The protocol described in this file is intended as a stopgap
    and is expected to be superseded by a solution in wayland-protocols.
    Clients should not assume this protocol will continue to exist in the
    future.
  </description>

  <interface name="shell_surface_intersection_observer_manager_v1" version="1">
    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the manager">
        Destroy the manager. Destroying the manager does not destroy objects
        created by the manager.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="get_observer">
      <description summary="get an intersection observer for the given surface">
        Get an intersection observer for the given surface.

        If a client intends to change the geometry of the surface based
        on observed intersections and intends to detect intersections
        in the same location after modifying the surface geometry,
        the client should use 'set_detection_region' to ensure the
        observed region matches the desired location.

        A compositor may wish to offer intersection information to
        only a subset of clients or surfaces. If the compositor's
        decision is influenced by the specific surface or requested
        intersection region, the compositor must wait for a
        'wl_surface.commit' following creation of the observer
        before making a descision.

        Clients may wait for a 'flags' event following the previously
        mentioned commit to make a decision about where to map the
        surface based on potential intersections, so compositors must
        respond with a 'flags' or 'finished' event following the commit
        to avoid blocking the client.
      </description>

      <arg name="observer" type="new_id" interface="shell_surface_intersection_observer_v1"/>
      <arg name="surface" type="object" interface="wl_surface"/>
    </request>
  </interface>

  <interface name="shell_surface_intersection_observer_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="observe intersections of surfaces and toplevels">
      A shell surface intersection observer allows a client to monitor
      a region relative to a wl_surface for intersecting toplevels.
    </description>

    <request name="destroy">
      <description summary="destroy the intersection observer">
        Destroys the object.
      </description>
    </request>

    <event name="finished">
      <description summary="no further events will be sent">
        The compositor is done sending events to this intersection observer.

        This event may be sent immediately if the compositor does not wish
        to provide intersection information for the surface, or if the
        compositor later decides to stop providing intersection information
        to the surface.
      </description>
    </event>

    <request name="set_detection_region">
      <description summary="sets the observed region">
        Sets the region the client wishes to observe intersections for.
        This region is relative to the geometry of the surface.

        When unset or set to null, the observation region matches the
        geometry of the surface.

        The detection region is double-buffered and must not take effect
        until 'wl_surface.commit' is called.
      </description>

      <arg name="region" type="object" interface="wl_region" allow-null="true"/>
    </request>

    <enum name="flags">
      <entry name="floating_toplevel"
             summary="a floating toplevel intersects with the region"
             value="1"/>
      <entry name="tiled_toplevel"
             summary="a tiled toplevel intersects with the region"
             value="2"/>
      <entry name="maximized_toplevel"
             summary="a maximized toplevel intersects with the region"
             value="4"/>
    </enum>

    <event name="flags">
      <description summary="intersections in the observed region have changed">
        This event reports the current state of intersections in the
        observed region. It is sent upon creation of the intersection
        observer and following any observed changes in the observed region.

        Window decorations should be included when checking if a toplevel
        intersects with the region.
      </description>

      <arg name="flags" type="uint" enum="flags"/>
    </event>
  </interface>
</protocol>
