<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="shell_seat_grab_v1">
  <copyright>
    Copyright © 2025 outfoxxed

    Permission to use, copy, modify, distribute, and sell this
    software and its documentation for any purpose is hereby granted
    without fee, provided that the above copyright notice appear in
    all copies and that both that copyright notice and this permission
    notice appear in supporting documentation, and that the name of
    the copyright holders not be used in advertising or publicity
    pertaining to distribution of the software without specific,
    written prior permission.  The copyright holders make no
    representations about the suitability of this software for any
    purpose.  It is provided "as is" without express or implied
    warranty.

    THE COPYRIGHT HOLDERS DISCLAIM ALL WARRANTIES WITH REGARD TO THIS
    SOFTWARE, INCLUDING ALL IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND
    FITNESS, IN NO EVENT SHALL THE COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY
    SPECIAL, INDIRECT OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES OR ANY DAMAGES
    WHATSOEVER RESULTING FROM LOSS OF USE, DATA OR PROFITS, WHETHER IN
    AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, NEGLIGENCE OR OTHER TORTIOUS ACTION,
    ARISING OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE USE OR PERFORMANCE OF
    THIS SOFTWARE.
  </copyright>

  <description summary="protocol for creating seat grabs">
    This protocol allows a seat grab to be taken in less restrictive
    ways than 'xdg_popup.grab'. It allows a greater set of surfaces to
    perform a grab, and allows client-defined actions such as menu
    closing animations to take place following the clearing of a grab.

    The key words "must", "must not", "required", "shall", "shall not",
    "should", "should not", "recommended",  "may", and "optional" in this
    document are to be interpreted as described in IETF RFC 2119.

    Warning! The protocol described in this file is intended as a stopgap
    and is expected to be superseded by a solution in wayland-protocols.
    Clients should not assume this protocol will continue to exist in the
    future.
  </description>

  <interface name="shell_seat_grab_manager_v1" version="1">
    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the manager">
        Destroy the manager. Destroying the manager does not destroy objects
        created by the manager.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="grab">
      <description summary="create a seat grab">
        This request creates a seat grab object. The compositor may
        respond with an 'active' event indicating the grab is now
        active or a 'cleared' event indicating it was denied.

        This request may be submitted with the serial number of a user
        event to inform the compositor that the grab has been requested
        as the result of a user action, or '0' if no serial is available.

        Compositors may deny a grab for any reason including a '0' serial
        or disallowed role, but may want to consider other conditions to
        allow the creation of a grab, such as being performed by a client
        with a newly created layer surface.
      </description>

      <arg name="grab" type="new_id" interface="shell_seat_grab_v1"/>
      <arg name="seat" type="object" interface="wl_seat" summary="the seat to grab"/>
      <arg name="serial" type="uint" summary="the serial of the user event"/>
    </request>
  </interface>

  <interface name="shell_seat_grab_v1" version="1">
    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the seat grab">
        This request destroys the seat grab. If active, the grab is cleared.

        If the grab is active, keyboard focus was requested for a surface prior
        to destruction, the surface is still focusable following destruction and
        leaving the surface keyboard focused makes sense for the compositor's
        focus model, the compositor should leave the surface keyboard focused.
        Otherwise, the compositor should re-determine keyboard focus following
        its usual procedure.
      </description>
    </request>

    <event name="cleared">
      <description summary="the compositor has cleared the grab">
        The compositor has cleared the seat grab. If this event
        is sent before an 'active' event, the compositor has
        declined to create the grab.

        The grab should be destroyed following this event.
      </description>
    </event>

    <event name="active">
      <description summary="the seat grab is now active">
        This event is sent when the seat grab comes into effect.
      </description>
    </event>

    <request name="set_keyboard_surface">
      <description summary="requests keyboard focus for a specific surface">
        Request that the compositor gives keyboard focus to the given
        surface.

        If this request is not sent, a null surface is requested,
        or the surface that currently has focus is destroyed,
        no surface will receive keyboard focus. 
      </description>

      <arg name="surface" type="object" interface="wl_surface" allow-null="true"/>
    </request>
  </interface>
</protocol>
