<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="shell_workspace_toplevel_management_v1">
  <copyright>
    Copyright © 2025 outfoxxed

    Permission to use, copy, modify, distribute, and sell this
    software and its documentation for any purpose is hereby granted
    without fee, provided that the above copyright notice appear in
    all copies and that both that copyright notice and this permission
    notice appear in supporting documentation, and that the name of
    the copyright holders not be used in advertising or publicity
    pertaining to distribution of the software without specific,
    written prior permission.  The copyright holders make no
    representations about the suitability of this software for any
    purpose.  It is provided "as is" without express or implied
    warranty.

    THE COPYRIGHT HOLDERS DISCLAIM ALL WARRANTIES WITH REGARD TO THIS
    SOFTWARE, INCLUDING ALL IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND
    FITNESS, IN NO EVENT SHALL THE COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY
    SPECIAL, INDIRECT OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES OR ANY DAMAGES
    WHATSOEVER RESULTING FROM LOSS OF USE, DATA OR PROFITS, WHETHER IN
    AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, NEGLIGENCE OR OTHER TORTIOUS ACTION,
    ARISING OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE USE OR PERFORMANCE OF
    THIS SOFTWARE.
  </copyright>

  <description summary="protocol for managing toplevels on a workspace">
    The workspace toplevel management protocol allows clients to observe
    and optionally manipulate toplevels in relation to workspaces as
    defined in the ext-workspace-v1 protocol.
    
    The key words "must", "must not", "required", "shall", "shall not",
    "should", "should not", "recommended",  "may", and "optional" in this
    document are to be interpreted as described in IETF RFC 2119.

    Warning! The protocol described in this file is intended as a stopgap
    and is expected to be superseded by a solution in wayland-protocols.
    Clients should not assume this protocol will continue to exist in the
    future.
  </description>

  <interface name="shell_workspace_toplevel_manager_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="acquires workspace toplevel management handles">
      The workspace toplevel manager global allows clients to acquire
      workspace toplevel management handles.
    </description>

    <request name="destroy">
      <description summary="destroy the manager">
        Destroy the workspace toplevel manager. Destroying the manager
        does not destroy objects created by the manager.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="get_handle">
      <description summary="get a workspace toplevel management handle">
        This request acquires a workspace toplevel management handle for
        a given workspace.

        If multiple 'ext_workspace_manager_v1' instances exist, transactional
        requests and events on the new handle refer to the manager that
        created the given workspace object.

        Toplevels referenced by events and responses must be part of the
        toplevel list given to this call or an 'invalid_toplevel' error
        will be raised.
      </description>

      <arg name="handle" type="new_id" interface="shell_workspace_toplevel_management_handle_v1"/>
      <arg name="workspace" type="object" interface="ext_workspace_handle_v1"/>
      <arg name="toplevel_list" type="object" interface="ext_foreign_toplevel_list_v1"/>
    </request>
  </interface>

  <interface name="shell_workspace_toplevel_management_handle_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="a handle to observe and manage toplevels present on a workspace">
      A workspace toplevel management handle allows observation of toplevels
      present on a workspace and their management.

      Upon creation of this object, the compositor must send 'capabilities'
      and 'enter' events for toplevels currently present on the workspace,
      and must send a 'ext_workspace_manager_v1.done' event regardless of
      if any toplevels are present.
    </description>

    <enum name="error">
      <entry name="invalid_toplevel"
             summary="a toplevel not from the provided toplevel list was used"
             value="1"/>
    </enum>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the handle">
        This request destroys the workspace toplevel management handle.
      </description>
    </request>

    <enum name="capabilities">
      <entry name="add_toplevel"
             summary="add_toplevel requests can be made on this workspace"
             value="1">
      </entry>
      <entry name="remove_toplevel"
             summary="remove_toplevel requests can be made on this workspace"
             value="2"/>
    </enum>

    <event name="capabilities">
      <description summary="the workspace's capabilities have been updated">
        This event changes the capabilities available for the workspace.

        It must be sent upon creation of the object even if no capabilities
        are available.

        This event is transactional and should not be acted upon until
        the 'ext_workspace_manager_v1.done' event is received.
      </description>

      <arg name="capabilities" type="uint" enum="capabilities"/>
    </event>

    <event name="enter">
      <description summary="a toplevel has entered the workspace">
        A toplevel has entered this workspace.

        This event is transactional and should not be acted upon until
        the 'ext_workspace_manager_v1.done' event is received.
      </description>

      <arg name="toplevel" type="object" interface="ext_foreign_toplevel_handle_v1"/>
    </event>

    <event name="leave">
      <description summary="a toplevel has left the workspace">
        A toplevel has left this workspace.

        This event is transactional and should not be acted upon until
        the 'ext_workspace_manager_v1.done' event is received.
      </description>

      <arg name="toplevel" type="object" interface="ext_foreign_toplevel_handle_v1"/>
    </event>

    <request name="add_toplevel">
      <description summary="add a toplevel to the workspace">
        This request asks the compositor to add the given toplevel to the workspace.
        Compositor policy dictates if this involves removing the toplevel from
        another workspace.

        This event is transactional and must not be considered until an
        'ext_workspace_manager_v1.commit' event has been sent.

        The compositor must send an 'ext_workspace_manager_v1.done' event after
        handling this request, regardless of if the toplevel was added.

        If adding the toplevel to this workspace involves removing it from another,
        the other workspace must be sent a 'leave' event before the 'done' event
        is sent.

        If the 'add_toplevel' capability is not present, the request must be
        ignored.
      </description>

      <arg name="toplevel" type="object" interface="ext_foreign_toplevel_handle_v1"/>
    </request>

    <request name="remove_toplevel">
      <description summary="remove a toplevel from the workspace">
        This request asks the compositor to remove the given toplevel from the workspace.
        Compositor policy dictates if this involves removing the toplevel from
        another workspace.

        This event is transactional and must not be considered until an
        'ext_workspace_manager_v1.commit' event has been sent.

        The compositor must send an 'ext_workspace_manager_v1.done' event after
        handling this request, regardless of if the toplevel was removed.

        If removing the toplevel from this workspace involves adding it to another,
        the other workspace must be sent an 'enter' event before the 'done' event
        is sent.

        If the 'remove_toplevel' capability is not present, the request must be
        ignored.
      </description>

      <arg name="toplevel" type="object" interface="ext_foreign_toplevel_handle_v1"/>
    </request>
  </interface>
</protocol>
