<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="shell_workspace_creation_v1">
  <copyright>
    Copyright © 2025 outfoxxed

    Permission to use, copy, modify, distribute, and sell this
    software and its documentation for any purpose is hereby granted
    without fee, provided that the above copyright notice appear in
    all copies and that both that copyright notice and this permission
    notice appear in supporting documentation, and that the name of
    the copyright holders not be used in advertising or publicity
    pertaining to distribution of the software without specific,
    written prior permission.  The copyright holders make no
    representations about the suitability of this software for any
    purpose.  It is provided "as is" without express or implied
    warranty.

    THE COPYRIGHT HOLDERS DISCLAIM ALL WARRANTIES WITH REGARD TO THIS
    SOFTWARE, INCLUDING ALL IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND
    FITNESS, IN NO EVENT SHALL THE COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY
    SPECIAL, INDIRECT OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES OR ANY DAMAGES
    WHATSOEVER RESULTING FROM LOSS OF USE, DATA OR PROFITS, WHETHER IN
    AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, NEGLIGENCE OR OTHER TORTIOUS ACTION,
    ARISING OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE USE OR PERFORMANCE OF
    THIS SOFTWARE.
  </copyright>

  <description summary="protocol allowing the creation of workspaces">
    Many compositors make use of workspaces that are created dynamically
    based on content or focus. This protocol aims to allow creation of
    workspaces in such environments by combining the intent to create
    a workspace with actions suitable to create one.

    This protocol additionally aims to make any logical workspace location
    or workspace type available to the client, through globals defined
    in this protocol or compositor-specific companion protocols.

    A client may attempt to discover potential creation methods by
    creating new workspace targets, checking their capabilities and
    destroying them without use.
    
    The key words "must", "must not", "required", "shall", "shall not",
    "should", "should not", "recommended",  "may", and "optional" in this
    document are to be interpreted as described in IETF RFC 2119.

    Warning! The protocol described in this file is intended as a stopgap
    and is expected to be superseded by a solution in wayland-protocols.
    Clients should not assume this protocol will continue to exist in the
    future.
  </description>

  <interface name="shell_workspace_creation_target_descriptor_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="opaque workspace creation target descriptor">
      The workspace creation target descriptor is an opaque object
      that describes where and how a workspace will be created.

      Because shell_workspace_creation_target_descriptor_v1 objects
      are created from multiple independent factory interfaces,
      the shell_workspace_creation_target_descriptor_v1 interface
      is frozen at version 1.
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the descriptor">
        Destroys the object.
      </description>
    </request>
  </interface>

  <interface name="shell_workspace_target_creation_manager_v1" version="1">
    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the manager">
        Destroy the manager. Destroying the manager does not destroy objects
        created by the manager.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="get_target">
      <description>
        This request creates a new workspace target from a given workspace
        target descriptor.

        The descriptor may be destroyed following this request.

        Because the target descriptor cannot be versioned, this request
        is used to create a versionable target from the descriptor.
      </description>

      <arg name="target" type="new_id" interface="shell_workspace_creation_target_v1"/>
      <arg name="descriptor" type="new_id" interface="shell_workspace_creation_target_descriptor_v1"/>
    </request>
  </interface>

  <interface name="shell_workspace_arbitrary_creation_manager_v1" version="1">
    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the manager">
        Destroy the manager. Destroying the manager does not destroy objects
        created by the manager.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="get_arbitrary_target">
      <description summary="create a workspace target relative to another workspace">
        This requests creates a workspace target that targets an arbitrary
        compositor chosen name and location for the workspace.
      </description>

      <arg name="descriptor" type="new_id" interface="shell_workspace_creation_target_descriptor_v1"/>
    </request>
  </interface>

  <interface name="shell_workspace_coordinate_creation_manager_v1" version="1">
    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the manager">
        Destroy the manager. Destroying the manager does not destroy objects
        created by the manager.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="get_coordinate_target">
      <description summary="create a workspace target at the given coordinates">
        This request creates a workspace target at the given coordinates in
        the compositor's workspace coordinate space. This coordinate space
        should match the one used in 'ext_workspace_handle_v1.coordinates'.

        A given set of coordinates may be unrepresentable or otherwise disallowed
        by the compositor, in which case the workspace target will be invalid.

        If a workspace already exists at the given coordinates, the resuling
        target should be valid and refer to the existing workspace.
      </description>

      <arg name="descriptor" type="new_id" interface="shell_workspace_creation_target_descriptor_v1"/>
      <arg name="coordinates" type="array"/>
    </request>
  </interface>

  <interface name="shell_workspace_relative_creation_manager_v1" version="1">
    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the manager">
        Destroy the manager. Destroying the manager does not destroy objects
        created by the manager.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="get_relative_target">
      <description summary="create a workspace target relative to another workspace">
        This request creates a workspace target at the given coordinate offset
        from another workspace. The workspace coordinate space should match the
        one used in 'ext_workspace_handle_v1.coordinates'.

        A given coordinate offset may be unrepresentable or otherwise disallowed
        by the compositor, in which case the workspace target will be invalid.

        If a workspace already exists at the given offset, the resuling
        target should be valid and refer to the existing workspace.
      </description>

      <arg name="descriptor" type="new_id" interface="shell_workspace_creation_target_descriptor_v1"/>
      <arg name="workspace" type="object" interface="ext_workspace_handle_v1"/>
      <arg name="offset" type="array" summary="coordinate offset from the given workspace"/>
    </request>
  </interface>

  <interface name="shell_workspace_creation_target_v1" version="1">
    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the manager">
        Destroy the manager. Destroying the manager does not destroy objects
        created by the manager.
      </description>
    </request>

    <description summary="a target for actions that may create or activate a target workspace">
      A workspace creation target is a target for actions that may create a new workspace
      if performed. It may refer to either an existing workspace, or act as a marker
      of where and how a new workspace should be created.
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the target">
        Destroy the workspace target. Destroying the target does not
        cancel committed requests.
      </description>
    </request>

    <enum name="capabilities">
      <entry name="create"
             summary="the targeted workspace can be created with only a request"
             value="1"/>
      <entry name="external"
             summary="the targeted workspace can be created through an extension protocol"
             value="2"/>
      <entry name="by_name"
             summary="the targeted workspace can be created by assigning a name"
             value="4"/>
      <entry name="nameable"
             summary="the targeted workspace can be named during creation"
             value="8"/>
      <entry name="activate"
             summary="the targeted workspace can be created by activating it"
             value="16"/>
      <entry name="add_toplevel"
             summary="the workspace toplevels can be created by adding a toplevel to it"
             value="32"/>
    </enum>

    <event name="capabilities">
      <description summary="update the capabilities of the workspace target">
        This event updates the capabilities of the workspace target.
        It must be sent upon creation of the target, and may be
        sent again at any point thereafter.

        A workspace target without any capabilities is considered to be
        invalid. An invalid target may be provided by the compositor
        if an unrepresentable, disallowed, or otherwise invalid workspace
        target is requested by the client.

        Clients are not required to check the capabilities of the target
        before attempting to use them, but such uses must result in failure.
      </description>

      <arg name="capabilities" type="uint" enum="capabilities"/>
    </event>

    <event name="success">
      <description summary="an action was successful">
        This event reports that a requested action was successful.

        Reported 'success' and 'failed' events correspond to actions
        in the order they were requested.
      </description>
    </event>

    <event name="failed">
      <description summary="an action was successful">
        This event reports that a requested action was not successful.
        This may be due to a missing capability or any other compositor
        determined reason.

        Reported 'success' and 'failed' events correspond to actions
        in the order they were requested.
      </description>
    </event>

    <request name="commit">
      <description summary="submit a sequence of actions">
        This request submits a sequence of creation actions to be
        performed atomically.

        Additional creation actions may be specified using
        a compositor-specific extension protocol.

        Following this request, the client will receive a series of 'success'
        or 'failed' events corresponding to the requested actions.

        The client may destroy the target object following this request if it
        does not care about the results of the actions or wishes to determine
        them in another way.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="create">
      <description summary="create the workspace">
        Asks the compositor to create the workspace target.
        This request is redundant if any other action is requested.

        This request must not take effect until committed.
        
        A 'success' or 'failed' event must be sent in response to this
        following a commit. The request should be considered successful
        if the workspace exists following the request, regardless
        of if its creation was a result of this request.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="set_name">
      <description summary="set the name of the targeted workspace">
        Asks the compositor to give a name to the targeted workspace.

        If the 'by_name' capability is present, assigning a name to the
        workspace is enough to ensure its creation. The workspace may
        still accept a name if the 'nameable' capability is present.

        This request must not take effect until committed.

        A 'success' or 'failed' event must be sent in response to this
        following a commit. The request should be considered successful
        if the workspace is active following the request, regardless
        of if its activation was a result of this request.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="activate">
      <description summary="activate the target workspace">
        Asks the compositor to active the workspace target.

        This request must not take effect until committed.

        A 'success' or 'failed' event must be sent in response to this
        following a commit. The request should be considered successful
        if the workspace is active following the request, regardless
        of if its activation was a result of this request.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="add_toplevel">
      <description summary="add a toplevel to the target workspace">
        Asks the compositor to move the given toplevel to the workspace
        target. This request should not activate the target workspace
        without an additional 'activate' request.

        This request must not take effect until committed.

        A 'success' or 'failed' event must be sent in response to this
        following a commit. The request should be considered successful
        if the toplevel is present on the workspace following the request,
        regardless of if its presence was a result of this request.
      </description>
    </request>
  </interface>
</protocol>
