<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="shell_wlr_foreign_toplevel_association_v1">
  <copyright>
    Copyright © 2025 outfoxxed

    Permission to use, copy, modify, distribute, and sell this
    software and its documentation for any purpose is hereby granted
    without fee, provided that the above copyright notice appear in
    all copies and that both that copyright notice and this permission
    notice appear in supporting documentation, and that the name of
    the copyright holders not be used in advertising or publicity
    pertaining to distribution of the software without specific,
    written prior permission.  The copyright holders make no
    representations about the suitability of this software for any
    purpose.  It is provided "as is" without express or implied
    warranty.

    THE COPYRIGHT HOLDERS DISCLAIM ALL WARRANTIES WITH REGARD TO THIS
    SOFTWARE, INCLUDING ALL IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND
    FITNESS, IN NO EVENT SHALL THE COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY
    SPECIAL, INDIRECT OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES OR ANY DAMAGES
    WHATSOEVER RESULTING FROM LOSS OF USE, DATA OR PROFITS, WHETHER IN
    AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, NEGLIGENCE OR OTHER TORTIOUS ACTION,
    ARISING OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE USE OR PERFORMANCE OF
    THIS SOFTWARE.
  </copyright>

  <description summary="protocol for association of ext and wlr foreign toplevel handles">
    This protocol allows a client to determine if an ext_foreign_toplevel_handle_v1
    and zwlr_foreign_toplevel_handle_v1 refer to the same toplevel.

    Compositor policy for exposing this protocol, ext-foreign-toplevel-list-v1
    and wlr-foreign-toplevel-management-unstable-v1 should match.

    The key words "must", "must not", "required", "shall", "shall not",
    "should", "should not", "recommended",  "may", and "optional" in this
    document are to be interpreted as described in IETF RFC 2119.

    Warning! The protocol described in this file is intended as a stopgap
    and is expected to be superseded by a solution in wayland-protocols.
    Clients should not assume this protocol will continue to exist in the
    future.
  </description>

  <interface name="shell_wlr_foreign_toplevel_association_manager_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="associates ext and wlr toplevel handles">
      A foreign toplevel pair is defined as a set of both a
      live ext_foreign_toplevel_handle_v1 object and a live
      zwlr_foreign_toplevel_handle_v1 object that refer to the same
      object in the compositor.

      Upon creation of the manager, 'associate' events must be sent for
      all existing foreign toplevel pairs. Following creation, an associate
      event must be sent whenever a new foreign toplevel pair is completed.

      Completion occurs whenever an ext_foreign_toplevel_handle_v1 and
      zwlr_foreign_toplevel_handle_v1 begin to exist simultaneously on
      the client. This happens immediately following an
      'ext_foreign_toplevel_list_v1.toplevel' or
      'zwlr_foreign_toplevel_management_v1.toplevel' event, once both
      referenced objects are live.

      Clients which only care about the current state can perform a
      roundtrip after binding this global.
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the manager">
        Destroys the manager object. All live associations will be resent
        if the manager is later rebound.
      </description>
    </request>

    <event name="associate">
      <description summary="associates an ext and wlr toplevel handle">
        This event associates an ext toplevel with a wlr toplevel.
      </description>

      <arg name="ext_toplevel" type="object" interface="ext_foreign_toplevel_handle_v1"/>
      <arg name="wlr_toplevel" type="object" interface="zwlr_foreign_toplevel_handle_v1"/>
    </event>
  </interface>
</protocol>
