<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="shell_foreign_toplevel_geometry_tracker_v1">
  <copyright>
    Copyright © 2025 outfoxxed

    Permission to use, copy, modify, distribute, and sell this
    software and its documentation for any purpose is hereby granted
    without fee, provided that the above copyright notice appear in
    all copies and that both that copyright notice and this permission
    notice appear in supporting documentation, and that the name of
    the copyright holders not be used in advertising or publicity
    pertaining to distribution of the software without specific,
    written prior permission.  The copyright holders make no
    representations about the suitability of this software for any
    purpose.  It is provided "as is" without express or implied
    warranty.

    THE COPYRIGHT HOLDERS DISCLAIM ALL WARRANTIES WITH REGARD TO THIS
    SOFTWARE, INCLUDING ALL IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND
    FITNESS, IN NO EVENT SHALL THE COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY
    SPECIAL, INDIRECT OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES OR ANY DAMAGES
    WHATSOEVER RESULTING FROM LOSS OF USE, DATA OR PROFITS, WHETHER IN
    AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, NEGLIGENCE OR OTHER TORTIOUS ACTION,
    ARISING OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE USE OR PERFORMANCE OF
    THIS SOFTWARE.
  </copyright>

  <description summary="protocol allowing clients to track foreign toplevel geometry">
    This protocol allows clients to track the geometry of toplevels
    relative to outputs or workspaces, enabling workspace overviews
    and window picking.

    This protocol is privileged and should be limited to trusted clients.

    The key words "must", "must not", "required", "shall", "shall not",
    "should", "should not", "recommended",  "may", and "optional" in this
    document are to be interpreted as described in IETF RFC 2119.

    Warning! The protocol described in this file is intended as a stopgap
    and is expected to be superseded by a solution in wayland-protocols.
    Clients should not assume this protocol will continue to exist in the
    future.
  </description>

  <interface name="shell_foreign_toplevel_geometry_tracker_manager_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="manager for geometry trackers">
      This global creates and synchronizes geometry trackers.
    </description>

    <enum name="error">
      <entry name="live_trackers"
             summary="destroyed geometry tracker manager while trackers were live"
             value="1"/>
    </enum>
      
    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the manager">
        Destroy the manager. Destroying the manager prior to
        the destruction of all trackers created by it is a protocol
        error, as the manager is responsible for synchronization.
      </description>
    </request>

    <event name="done">
      <description summary="all geometry tracker events have been sent">
        This event signals that all events related to created geometry
        trackers and their members have been sent.
      </description>
    </event>

    <request name="get_output_tracker">
      <description summary="create a geometry tracker for a given output">
        Creates a geometry tracker which tracks toplevels on a given output.
      </description>

      <arg name="tracker" type="new_id" interface="shell_foreign_toplevel_geometry_tracker_v1"/>
      <arg name="output" type="object" interface="wl_output"/>
    </request>

    <request name="get_workspace_tracker">
      <description summary="create a geometry tracker for a given workspace">
        Creates a geometry tracker which tracks toplevels on a given workspace.
      </description>

      <arg name="tracker" type="new_id" interface="shell_foreign_toplevel_geometry_tracker_v1"/>
      <arg name="workspace" type="object" interface="ext_workspace_handle_v1"/>
    </request>
  </interface>

  <interface name="shell_foreign_toplevel_geometry_tracker_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="tracks relative geometry of intersecting objects">
      A geometry tracker tracks the relative geometry of toplevels
      intersecting with an output or workspace.

      Upon creation, an 'area' event must be sent.
    </description>

    <enum name="error">
      <entry name="reset_toplevel_list"
             summary="attempted to assign a toplevel list to the tracker multiple times"
             value="1"/>
      <entry name="destroyed_toplevel_list"
             summary="toplevel list used in a geometry tracker was destroyed"
             value="2"/>
    </enum>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the tracker">
        Destroy the tracker. All tracker members must receive a
        finished event following this request.
      </description>
    </request>

    <event name="area">
      <description summary="reports the geometry of the tracked area">
        This event reports the geometry of the tracked area.

        Reported width and height should match the dimensions of the
        tracked area in logical pixels.

        This event must be sent upon creation of the tracker, and
        whenever the tracked area changes. This event is double-buffered
        and must be followed by a
        'shell_foreign_toplevel_geometry_tracker_manager_v1.done' event.
      </description>

      <arg name="width" type="int"/>
      <arg name="height" type="int"/>
    </event>

    <event name="margins">
      <description summary="reports insets into the tracked area">
        This event reports margins into the tracked area where toplevels
        may not normally be placed, such as exclusive zones of layer
        surfaces. Clients may use this information to avoid showing
        gaps in visual representations of the tracked area.

        Reported margins must be in the same coordinate space as
        those reported by 'area'.

        This event may be sent upon creation of the tracker, and
        whenever insets change. This event is double-buffered
        and must be followed by a
        'shell_foreign_toplevel_geometry_tracker_manager_v1.done' event.
      </description>

      <arg name="left" type="int"/>
      <arg name="top" type="int"/>
      <arg name="right" type="int"/>
      <arg name="bottom" type="int"/>
    </event>

    <event name="entered">
      <description name="an entity has entered the tracker area">
        This event reports that a toplevel has entered the tracking
        area. Untracked entities must not receive 'entered' events.
      </description>

      <arg name="member" type="new_id" interface="shell_foreign_toplevel_geometry_tracker_member_v1"/>
    </evnt>

    <request name="track_toplevels">
      <description summary="begins tracking toplevels">
        This request asks the compositor to track all toplevels created by the
        given toplevel list that enter the tracking area.

        Upon request, all toplevels that qualify as members of the tracker
        must be provided via an 'enter' event.

        Attempting to set the toplevel list more than once is an error, as
        is destroying the toplevel list prior to the destruction of
        this object.
      </description>

      <arg name="list" type="object" interface="ext_foreign_toplevel_list_v1"/>
    </request>
  </interface>

  <interface name="shell_foreign_toplevel_geometry_tracker_member_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="tracked entity visible on a geometry tracker">
      A toplevel tracked by a geometry tracker.

      Upon creation, toplevel, geometry, and optionally stacking order
      events must be sent by the compositor.
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the member">
        Destroys the tracker member object.
      </description>
    </request>

    <event name="left">
      <description summary="the toplevel has left the tracked area">
        The toplevel has left the tracked area. A toplevel must not be
        considered to have left until the toplevel's geometry has no
        intersection with the geometry tracker.

        Following this event, the member object should be destroyed and no more
        events will be sent to it. If the toplevel later re-enters the tracked
        area it will do so as a new object.

        This event is double-buffered and must be followed by a
        'shell_foreign_toplevel_geometry_tracker_manager_v1.done' event.
      </description>
    </event>

    <event name="geometry">
      <description summary="geometry of the toplevel has changed">
        New toplevel geometry information is available.
        This event is sent upon creation of the member object or changes
        to the toplevel's geometry.

        Compositor policy dictates which window decorations are included
        in the toplevel's geometry, but excluding non-window extents
        such as shadows is recommended.
        
        This event is double-buffered and must be followed by a
        'shell_foreign_toplevel_geometry_tracker_manager_v1.done' event.
      </description>

      <arg name="x" type="int"/>
      <arg name="y" type="int"/>
      <arg name="width" type="int"/>
      <arg name="height" type="int"/>
    </event>

    <event name="above">
      <description summary="the toplevel is now above another">
        This event reports that the toplevel is now directly above the
        given sibling in Z-order.

        This event is double-buffered and must be followed by a
        'shell_foreign_toplevel_geometry_tracker_manager_v1.done' event.
      </description>

      <arg name="sibling" type="object" interface="shell_foreign_toplevel_geometry_tracker_member_v1"/>
    </event>

    <event name="below">
      <description summary="the toplevel is now below another">
        This event reports that the toplevel is now directly below the
        given sibling in Z-order.

        This event is double-buffered and must be followed by a
        'shell_foreign_toplevel_geometry_tracker_manager_v1.done' event.
      </description>

      <arg name="sibling" type="object" interface="shell_foreign_toplevel_geometry_tracker_member_v1"/>
    </event>

    <event name="toplevel">
      <description summary="this member has been marked as a toplevel">
        This event sets the toplevel the tracker member refers to. This
        event can only be sent once, prior to the first 'done' event
        following the creation of the member object.

        A 'left' event must be sent upon closure of the toplevel.

        This event is double-buffered and must be followed by a
        'shell_foreign_toplevel_geometry_tracker_manager_v1.done' event.
      </description>

      <arg name="toplevel" type="object" interface="ext_foreign_toplevel_handle_v1"/>
    </event>
  </interface>
</protocol>
